Guide to the John H. Peatling Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
John H. Peatling Papers
1960-2007
RG 233
Yale University Divinity School Library
7.5
(18 boxes)
This collection documents the research and writings of Yale Divinity School graduate John H. Peatling, who was a specialist in empirical psychology and statistics with a particular interest in the cognitive development of religious and moral thinking. The collection also documents the International Seminar on Religious Education and Values, which Peatling founded with John Hull in 1977.
Peatling, John H.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peatling family, 2009
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
1926 Dec 15 Born in Kalamazoo, Michigan to John Howard Peatling, Sr. and Esther Rose Peatling. He was active in musical groups through high school and college.
1949 Graduated from Western Michigan University with a B.A.
1949 Jul 31 Married Jane Cobb. They had three children, Jane Ellen Duffy (4 Mar 1952), Karen Ann Crouch (20 Nov 1955), and Mary Elizabeth McCorkle (24 Dec 1957). Jane Cobb Peatling died 2 Nov 1970.
1952 B.D. in Parish Ministry from Yale University Divinity School.
1953 S.T.M. in Liturgics and the History of Doctrine from Yale University Divinity School.
1955 Ordained to the Christian Priesthood in the Diocese of Michigan of The Protestant Episcopal Church.
1960 Moved to Connecticut to work for the National Episcopal Church developing Christian education materials.
1971-1980s Worked for the Character Research Project in Union College, Schenectady, New York, first as the Assistant Director, then as Director of Basic Research.
1972 Apr 2 Married Lucie W. Barber.
1973 Ph.D. in Religious Education from New York University.
1974 Received the Founders Day Award from New York University.
1977 Founded the International Seminar on Religious Education and Values with John Hull. The first meeting was held in Birmingham, England in 1978.
1984-1988 Served as Rector for St. Stephen's Episcopal Church, Schenectady and then became Rector Emeritus.
1991 Death of his wife, Lucie Barber.
2007 May 15 Died in Niskayuna, New York.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the research and writings of John H. Peatling, a Yale Divinity School alumnus. Peatling was a specialist in empirical psychology and statistics. He was particularly interested in the cognitive development of religious and moral thinking. He worked for the Character Research Project at Union College from 1971 until the early 1980s, first as the Assistant Director, then as the Director of Basic Research. John Peatling and John Hull founded the International Seminar on Religious Education and Values, in 1977, with the first meeting taking place in Birmingham, England in 1978 and the second meeting at Union College in Schenectady, New York in 1980. The collection is primarily comprised of his writings, research data and tools, and material regarding the International Seminar on Religious Education and Values (ISREV).
Series I, Writings, is divided into two subseries: Writings by John H. Peatling and Writings by Lucie Barber and Others. The Writings by Peatling are arranged alphabetically and include manuscripts, bound manuscripts and theses, and published articles, book chapters, and books. The Writings by Lucie Barber and Others are arranged chronologically and include manuscripts by Lucie Barber, Peatling's wife who also worked at the Character Research Project at Union College, and correspondence regarding the manuscripts. There are a few published works by others included in the collection.
Series II, Research Data and Tools, is divided into two subseries: Research Data and Research Tools. The Research Data includes the data collected for Peatling's Ph.D. thesis, Project R&D/23, A Study of Thinking About Biblical Material, in addition to other research projects he worked on. Research Tools includes tools created by Peatling and published tools used by Peatling in his research.
Series III, International Seminar on Religious Education and Values (ISREV), contains materials documenting the inception of the seminar, planning, correspondence, meeting information, membership directories, and collegial papers presented at meetings between 1978 and 1996. Series IV, Personal and Biographical, is small containing one folder of biographical information, Peatling's copy of The Book of Common Prayer, and material relating to conferences and professional affiliations.
Arrangement
I. Writings, 1964-1983
II. Research Data and Tools, 1960-1994
III. International Seminar on Religious Education and Values (ISREV), 1977-1996
IV. Personal and Biographical, 1962-2007
Christian education -- Psychology; Religious education; Peatling, John H.; International Seminar on Religious Education and Values
- Writings, Series I
  - Writings by John H. Peatling
    - An Approach to the Micro-Analysis of Response Patterns Elicited by the Device Entitled Thinking About the Bible1, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Assessing the Feeling of Justice: Five Stories Keyed to Developmental Aspects of a Piagetian Sense of Justice, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Career Devlopment: Designing Self, by John H. Peatling and David V. Tiedeman, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Definitions for Sixteen Elements in a Model Personality, by John H. Peatling and David V. Tiedeman, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Designing Self: A Group Theory of Constructionist Personality Reconstruction (Bound Copy), by John H. Peatling and David V. Tiedeman, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Finnish Students' Responses to a Moral Puzzle, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - From Noise to Insight: An Exploration of the Realms of Intuition, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - From Noise to Insight: An Exploration of the Realms of Intuition (Bound Copy), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - In Celebration of And. Book Chapter in Modern Masters of Religious Education, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - The Incidence of Concrete and Abstract Religious Thinking in the Interpretation of Three Bible Stories by Pupils Enrolled in Grades Four Through Twelve in Selected Schools in the Episcopal Church in the United States of America (PhD Dissertation), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Liturgical Suggestions for Celebrating the Para-Feasts of the Lord of All Distributions, the Holy Probability, Blessed Student, and the Memory of Kurt Gödel, Book Chapter in Aesthetic Dimensions of Religious Education, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - MGT: Continuing Ideas/Investigations, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Moral Education: Another View, The New Review of Books and Religion, Vol.11, No.6, 1978. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Not Without Mystery, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
    - On Beyond Goldman: Religious Thinking and the 1970s, Learning for Living, Vol.16, No.3, 1977, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - A Piagetian Perspective on the Development of an Aspect of the Sense of Justice, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - A Piagetian Perspective on the Development of an Aspect of the Sense of Justice (3 Bound Copies), 1975 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Psychology and Religion: Uncommon Partners, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Religious Education in a Psychological Key (Galley Proof), 1981 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
    - Religious Education in a Psychological Key (Index), 1981 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Religious Thinking as an Assessable Construct in Children, Youth and Adults (Bound Copy), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Research and Religious Education, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Revised Guidelines for an Annual Review of Research: Religious Education, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Signs of Structure and Signs of Dissonance: Adult Responses to a Piagetian Moral Puzzle, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - The Slow Learner and Religious Education, Learning for Living, Vol.14, No.3, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - A Statement About a Model of Personality, by Lucie Barber and John H. Peatling, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Theories of Development, A Dictionary of Religious Education, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Truth Telling and Peer Protection: A Report, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    - Truth Telling and Peer Protection: A Report (Bound Copy), 1974 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Writings by Lucie Barber and Others
    - Religious Education of Preschool Chiildren, includes correspondence with James Michael Lee, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Religious Education of Preschool Chiildren, includes correspondence with James Michael Lee, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Education in Christian Values (Manuscript), includes correspondence with James Michael Lee, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Printed Material by Others, 1964, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Research Data and Tools
  - Research Data
    - Project R&D/23, A Study of Thinking About Biblical Material - A Problem Check List, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - R&D/23, Material Sent to Thesis Committtee re R&D/23, Vol.1, General and Initial Plans, 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - R&D/23, Material Sent to Thesis Committee, Vo.1, Pre-Test & Field Test A, 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - R&D/23, Material Sent to Thesis Committee, Vo.1, Pre-Test & Field Test B, 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - R&D/23, Material Sent to Thesis Committee, Vo.2, Revised Instrument, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - R&D/23, Material Sent to Thesis Committee, Vo.2, Field Test C, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - R&D/23, Ph.D. Thesis Outline, Jul 1969 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - R&D/23, Material Sent to Thesis Committee, Vo.2, Survey Sample, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - R&D/23, Field Test A, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - R&D/23, Field Test A, Comments from Students, p.10, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - R&D/23, Field Test A Student Comments, p.17, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - R&D/23, Field Test A Student Comments, p.24, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - R&D/23, Grade 7, Story A, 19 Oct 1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - R&D/23, Grade 8, Story A, 19 Oct 1968 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - R&D/23, Grade 9, Story A, 19 Oct 1968 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - R&D/23, Grade 7, Story B, 19 Oct 1968 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - R&D/23, Grade 8, Story B, 19 Oct 1968 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - R&D/23, Grade 9, Story B, 19 Oct 1968 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - R&D/23, Grade 7, Story C, 19 Oct 1968 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - R&D/23, Grade 8, Story C, 19 Oct 1968 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - R&D/23, Grade 9, Story C, 19 Oct 1968 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - R&D/23, Lambda-Mattrices 3rd Grade, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - R&D/23, School Data Sheets, FTC (Restricted until 2070), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 15-17)
    - R&D/23 Field Test C, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - R&D/23, A Coding Manual for R&D/23 (FTC), 1970 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - R&D/23, FTC, MISU: "Mental Ages, A Procedure for the Calculation of...", 1970 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - R&D/23, Study of Criteria, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
    - R&D/23, Study of Intelligence Scores, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - R&D/23, Computer Programs, Variable Listings, Studies of Significance Levels, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - R&D/23, Study of Means, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 8-10)
    - R&D/23, Summary Report, Thesis (Copy No.1), 1971 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - R&D/23, Summary Report, Thesis (Copy No.2), 1972 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - R&D/23, Miscellaneous Studies, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - R&D/23, Field Test B, Item Analysis, Tables 1-8, 9-56, 57-65, 66-70, 1968-1969 (Box OV 9)
    - Letters to God - Children's. Data from A. Hickson, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Theses Notes, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - ASynthesizing Study of Studies of Elements..., 1972 (Box 10, Folder 3-6)
    - Five Cries from Mid-Life: A Questionnaire for Adults, Nov 1977 (Box 10, Folder 7-10)
    - Thinking About Justice Study, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 11-12)
    - Thinking About Jusctice Study, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Justice the Search for Order, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 2-6)
    - SR&D-"Life Span, Divisions of" (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Research Tools
    - Attitude Inventory, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Describing Personality, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Readiness for Religion: Light, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Readiness for Religion: Sheep and Shepherds, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Readiness for Religion: The Importance of Bread, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Self-Regard Scales: Published Formats, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Thinking About Justice, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Thinking About My Religion, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Thinking About the Bible, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Thinking About the Bible (Includes Audio Tape), 1979 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Torrance Tests of Creative Thinking, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Torrance Tests of Creative Thinking, Figural Test - Form A, 1966 (Box 12)
    - Torrance Tests of Creative Thinking, Verbal Test - Form A, 1966 (Box 12)
    - Torrance Tests of Creative Thinking, Verbal Test - Form B, 1966 (Box 13)
    - Torrance Tests of Creative Thinking, Examiner's Kit (For Verbal Test, Forms A & B), 1966 (Box 13)
    - Torrance Test of Creative Thinking, Figural Test - Form B, 1966 (Box 14)
- International Seminar on Religious Education and Values (ISREV)
  - ISREV I
    - Planning, Invitation, and Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - List of Participants and Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Program, Handouts, Notes, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Papers, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 4-6)
    - Transcripts of Tapes Recorded at Meeting, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Post-Meeting Publications and Correspondence, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Religious Education and Values Newsletter, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Uncommon Partners, Manuscript and Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - ISREV II
    - Proposal, 1978-1979 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Activities Fall 1979 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Mar 1980 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Invitations and Responses, 1979-1980 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Registration and Correspondence, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Planning, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Planning, Registration, and Financial Information, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Packet Given to Participants, 7-11 Jul 1980 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Notes from Conference, Jul 1980 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Papers, 1979-1980 (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
    - Papers, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - ISREV III
    - Official Mailings, 1979-1982 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Pre-Seminar Information from John Hull, Jun 1982 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Interest Groups and Collegial Papers Titles, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Letter from John Hull, Aug 1982 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Report and Papers, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - ISREV IV
    - Planning Committee Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Invitations and Responses, 1983-1984 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Collegial Papers Note Cards, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence regarding Collegial Papers, 1983-1984 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Papers, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 3-5)
    - Program Planning, 1983-1984 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Preregistration Packet, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Meeting Packet, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Photographs from Meeting, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Post-Meeting Correspondence, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - ISREV V
    - Attendance, Emmaus, Swords, Ireland, 24-29 Jun 1986 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - JHP's "Second" Collegial Paper: Hagar the Horrible, 24-29 Jun 1986 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Major Presentations, 24-29 Jun 1986 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Business Meeting, 27 Jun 1986 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Preliminary Materials from Plannin Committee, 1986 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Focus Groups, 24-29 Jun 1986 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Collegial Papers: Texts of Selected Papers, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Post-Seminar Correspondence, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - ISREV VII
    - Minutes of Business Meetings, 28-29 Jun 1990 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - ISREV VIII
    - General Business Meeting Minutes, 28 Aug 1992 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Management Committee Meeting Minutes, 28 Aug 1992 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - ISREV IX
    - Mailing List and Meeting Information, 1994, 1996 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Directory of Members, 1994 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - ISREV X
    - Directory of Members, 1996 (Box 18, Folder 8)
- Personal and Biographical, Series IV
  - Biographical Information regarding John H. Peatling and Lucie Barber, 1970, 1971, 2007 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Book of Common Prayer (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Professional Affiliations and Conferences
    - ISTREC (C) - Meeting Information, 1962-1966 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - IDIOTS - Mailing List, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 11)